(upbeat music)
- Hello English nerders,
welcome back to the English pod.
My name is Marco.
- And my name is Katherine.
And today we're talking
about being on the road.
- Yeah, we're gonna be on the road,
but we're gonna encounter
a little bit of a car problems.
- My favorite kind.
- Yeah, I think it's happened to everyone,
you're on the road or maybe
you're coming back from work,
you get a flat tie or something
happens to your car, right?
- And it's always when you're in a rush.
- And most of the time it's raining.
- Yeah.
- We're just knowing,
so all of this circumstance
is definitely, well, they
don't help, let's just say.
All right, so before we
listen to this dialogue,
let's take a look at some of the
words in today's vocabulary preview.
- Very capillary preview.
- All right, so we're gonna
take a look at two words.
They're kind of strange, I
don't know, kind of difficult
to understand, so that's
where we're gonna explain them.
The first one is spew, to spew.
- It's a verb, okay?
It's to spew, well, what
can spew volcano can spew?
- Exactly.
- An engine can spew, a person can spew.
- Yeah, that's not very nice.
- No.
- So basically, it's to
like expel or to shoot out,
shoot out from your
mouth or something liquid.
So in the case of a person, right?
- So if a person spews, it means a person
throws up, but it's usually very forceful.
All right, it's very messy.
A volcano can spew lava.
- Exactly.
- So a volcano is spewing lava.
Now, for the next word that we have,
it's an informal way of saying
that something is broken.
- Because it's busted.
- It's busted, my DVD player is busted.
- Man, my phone is busted.
- So it's an informal way,
very popular, very common,
I would say, to describe
that something is not working.
I don't think many people actually
say, well, it's broken or it's damaged.
- Yeah, they're pretty much mixed, I
think, but you will definitely hear busted
if you're talking to
native English speakers.
- Or even, like, for example, your arm.
Oh, he's got a busted arm.
- Exactly, so busted.
- All right, so let's listen to
our dialogue for the first time.
Let's see what's going
on with this car trouble,
and then we'll come back
and explain some things.
(upbeat music)
- Harry, nice car.
- What seems to be the problem?
- I don't know, the stupid old car started
being white smoke, and it just died on me.
Luckily, I managed to
start it up and drive it here.
What do you think it is?
- Not sure yet.
How about you pop the
hood, and we can take a look?
- Mm, doesn't look good.
- What do you mean?
My daddy gave me this car
for my birthday last month.
It's brand new.
- Well, Missy, the white smoke that you saw
has steamed from the radiator.
You overheated your
engines, so now the
pistons are busted and
so is your transmission.
You should have call us, and we could
have told you over here when your car died.
- So, how long is this gonna take an hour?
- I'm afraid a bit more than that.
We need to order the spare parts,
take apart your electrical
system, fuel pump,
and engine, and then
put it back together again.
You were gonna have to leave
it here for at least two weeks.
- What? How am I supposed
to go to school, or go shopping?
This is not happening.
(upbeat music)
- So if I were the mechanic,
I would not be very
happy to be dealing
with someone like this girl.
(laughing)
- I think it's, well, maybe it's a little
bit stereotypical that we put it as a girl
because guys and girls, so many people
don't know anything about cars or mechanics.
- And in the states,
there's a lot of female
mechanics too, so it's,
you know, it's mixed.
- But definitely it's something
that happens all the time
and probably the mechanic
will overcharge her as well
because apparently she
doesn't know what she's doing.
- And that's one of the
reasons we wanna give you
the vocabulary to deal
with these situations.
So let's look at some of those car
words in today's language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, so we're gonna take a look
at very specific words related to
cars and the engines and everything.
So let's start with the first one.
- Radiator.
All right, so the radiator of the car.
- So radiator is something
that you normally find
in the front of the car near the engine.
It usually gets very, very hot, right?
- Yeah.
- So one of the big
issues is radiators getting
too hot because there's
no way to cool them down.
- So if you live in a place
that's very hot, the radiator
keeps your engine cool
because it has water in it.
So if it overheats or maybe you
didn't put enough water in there
then it'll start spewing
steam like in this dialogue.
- And if you have a
problem with your radiator,
you could actually do a lot of damage to
your engine which is why this is important.
- Exactly, and that's what
happened in this dialogue.
So a radiator.
Now because the radiator wasn't
working though, it overheated
the engine and he said they
had some busted pistons.
- So broken pistons, pistons are important
because they're kind of like
valves that go up and down.
- Right, so inside your engine
you have many explosions
and the pistons move up and down
and that's what actually moves your car.
- Right, and so pistons in
general are things in mechanics.
So like a trumpet has pistons,
things that go up and down
and that allow for the flow
of air or something like that.
Very good, so that's a piston.
And well, another very common
mechanic term is the transmission.
- All right, so the transmission, what
happens if your transmission dies?
Can you still drive?
- You basically can't move or
maybe you only have one gear
or two gears.
And so think about
transmission is coming from
the word to transmit,
that means to transfer.
- So this is the part
of the car that transfers
energy or the power
to actually move the car.
So the transmission.
- And we've got the mechanic who says, well,
we've got to order you some spare parts.
So first let's look at the word spare.
What's another word for spare?
- Additional, maybe extra.
- Right, so spare means
extra parts are well pieces.
So we're talking about
ordering a new transmission,
new pistons, things to
replace the broken things.
- Spare parts.
So this is where you go to the mechanic
to get some spare parts
and get them installed.
- You probably don't have
many spare parts at home, right?
- You got a transmission lying around.
- Oh yeah, so spare parts.
And the last word that we're
gonna take a look at is a fuel pump.
- Okay, so a pump is, you
could have a bike pump.
- A water pump, water pumps.
So these are something
that we use very, very often,
but a fuel pump is something that allows
gas gasoline to get into your engine.
- So it's basically a device that pushes
gasoline into the engine, so you can start.
And that's the same
thing with the water pump.
It's a device that pushes water.
- Or an air pump is something that pushes
air into your tires and your bicycle.
- Exactly, so a fuel pump,
water pump, et cetera.
- Wow, I feel like we
know a lot about cars.
- Yeah, apparently we do, see?
- All right, so now that we've taken
a look at all of these great words,
let's move on to a couple
of phrases in fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
- All right, these are
phrases that you hear
sometimes when you're
talking about electronics,
but in today's lesson, we're
also talking about specific
car phrases so you can hear
these all the time at the mechanics.
- Right, and the first one is
the car suddenly died on me.
- All right, to die on.
So we keep these two
words together die on, man.
So while you were driving, your car died.
It stopped moving.
- So that means that it
doesn't work anymore.
And it's not only for cars, right?
You can say my MP3 player died on me today.
- Exactly, and what it
means is it's not like you left it
and you forgot about
it and you tried it again
that didn't work, it means while you're using it, it dies, it does work.
- Exactly.
So I think this phrase is a good
one to give some other examples.
- So let's listen.
- Example one.
- My CD player died on me
and I had to listen to the radio.
- Example two.
- Get that medicine over here faster.
This guy's gonna die on me.
- Example three.
- I forgot to charge my mobile phone.
It's gonna die on me soon.
- And so this next one
is a phrase you hear.
The first thing you hear maybe, when
you tell someone you have a car problem.
- Right, you tell them to pop the hood.
- Or let's pop the hood.
So this means let's open
the front part of the car,
the hood to look at the engine, transmission, all those parts.
- Exactly.
So you can say open the hood,
but the most common one is pop the hood.
- So the reason is because
there's a little spring
and you have to pull inside the car
and it goes pop and there's a little jump.
- Yeah, exactly.
- So it's literally popping.
- Right, or you can also say the
trunk, the back part of the car.
- Hey, can you pop the trunk for me?
I've gotta put some stuff inside.
- Exactly, so pop the hood, pop the trunk.
- And next we've got this girl actually,
who's talking about her car
because she just got this car.
So it's another way to say it's a new car.
- It's brand new.
- Is that more new than new?
- It's like newer, newer than new.
- All right, so brand, you
think about brands like Ford
or Gucci, these are brands, but brand
new means, she maybe got it like today.
- So it's brand new, it's very, very new.
- Did you see my brand new watch?
- Oh, it is nice, forget it.
All right, so brand new.
And well, the last phrase that we have
for you today is to take apart something.
- All right, so this is very
popular with young children,
like they like to take things apart
so they can find out how they work,
but to take up more it means to
take all the pieces and to pull them out.
- Yeah, I used to do that
a lot when I was a kid,
I used to take apart any electronic
devices, kind of see how it works,
and then I would try to
put it back together again.
- That's why you're so smart.
- Well, it never really worked.
It worked half the time.
- So the problem is always putting
them back together again, right?
- Exactly, so you can take it apart,
but then you put it back together,
and there's always a screw missing or a
screw that's extra or two or three parts.
- Not a good sign.
- All right, so we've taken a
look at a lot of great words
and phrases, so let's listen to
this dialogue for the last time.
(upbeat music)
- Howdy, nice car, what
seems to be the problem?
- I don't know, the stupid old car started
being white smoke and it just died on me.
Luckily, I managed to
start it up and drive it here.
What do you think it is?
- Not sure yet.
- How about you pop the
hood and we could take a look?
- Mm, doesn't look good.
- What do you mean?
My daddy gave me this car
for my birthday last month.
It's brand new.
- Well, Missy, the white smoke that
you saw is steamed from the radiator.
You overheated your
engines, so now the
pistons are busted and
so is your transmission.
You should have call us and we could
have told you over here when your car died.
- Oh, so how long is
this gonna take an hour?
- I'm afraid a bit more than that.
We need to order the spare parts.
Take apart your electrical
system, fuel pump,
and engine, and then
put it back together again.
You were gonna have to leave
it here for at least two weeks.
- What?
How am I supposed to go
to school or go shopping?
This is not happening.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so car travel.
Have you ever had like
any very serious car travel
or like something weird
happened to your car?
- Actually, the week before
I decided to leave Chicago,
I had this 1991 Honda Civic
hatchback, so only two doors.
- Nice.
- And I was driving home from work, I
was on the highway, had the radio on,
the windows open, and
then two, two, two, two.
- It died.
- It died in the middle of the highway during rush hour, right?
So that's when there's tons of
cars, and I didn't know what to do.
Some calling people, and then all the
sudden, I see someone tapping on my window,
and there's cars
everywhere, and it's this guy.
And he's like, "Listen,
do you need a hand?
" I said, "Yes, so I put the car in
neutral so that there's no break.
" And he pushed it to a side
road and gave me a right home.
He was the coolest guy who's so nice,
and he was just there with his truck.
He's the gardener, and
just gave me right home.
It was super, super cool.
- Wow.
- And so it turns out my engine dot.
No, the engine was new, it
was a transmission, it was shot.
It was totally broken.
- Wow.
- But I was very lucky to
have such a kind person.
- Yeah, that's a good story,
because usually people
are too afraid, or maybe
a little bit reluctant to stop
and see if you're okay,
or if you need a ride,
or something, because you can't really
trust people these days, but it's good.
Once I saw somebody on the side of the
road and had a flat tire, it was two girls,
and they didn't know what
to do, so I was passing by.
It was actually raining.
And I was like, "Hey, do
you guys need a hand?
" And they're
like, "Yeah, please.
" And we can't locate
my dad or whatever,
so I was like, "Change in the
tire, it's not a big deal, right?
" And then they're like, "Oh, I
think... " And they wanted to tip me.
They wanted to give me some money.
And they're like, "Oh,
please say this is just so kind.
You're time, and you're all wet.
" And I'm like, "No,
no, don't worry about it.
" - Oh, it's just a
nice thing to do, too.
If you know anything
about cars, I mean, or
if you can offer
someone a lift, I know it's
not terribly safe to ride with strangers,
but this guy totally helped me out, so...
- Nice.
All right, well, maybe
you guys have some cool
or maybe some
interesting stories of what's
happened with your cars, or
maybe you've helped somebody out.
So come to our website at
www.EnglishPod.com and let us know.
- And of course, if you have any questions
about the vocabulary or phrases that you
heard today, please
ask a way, don't
hesitate, and we'll, again, we
hope to see you on the website.
- All right, we'll see you guys there.
- Bye.